The Light

Poul Anderson

In its quiet, reticent way (not referring to the story's style, which is on the hectic side, but to its denouement), this tale of the first moon trip packs one of the biggest wallops of any science fiction story I have ever read. It is about an invention that has not yet been "discovered"—but that was used once, well over 400 years ago! On a first reading, the story infuriated me. "Nonsense!" I cried. But I could not get it out of my mind; it haunted me. And I'll wager that it will haunt you, too.

And remember—It could be true. If it really did happen, you can be sure that the original inventor would have suppressed his discovery "for the good of humanity"—and to save his neck—and history would not have been at all changed.

You've got to realize this is the biggest secret since the Manhattan Project. Maybe bigger than that. Your life has been investigated since you got out of rompers and—

No, blast it! We're not a gang of power-nutty militarists. Think I wouldn't like to yell the truth to all the world?

But it might touch off the war. And everybody knows the war will mean the end of civilization.

I should think that you, as a historian, could see our reasons. Machiavelli is the symbol of cold-blooded realism . . . and you don't have to tell me that he was only an exceptionally clear-headed patriot. I've read The Prince and the Discourses.

Frankly, I'm surprised that you're surprised. Just because I know enough math and physics to be in Astro, why should I be an uncultured redneck? No, sir, I've traveled around and I spent as much time in the museums of Europe as I did in the taverns.

I'll admit my companions on the Moon trip looked a bit askance at me because of that. They weren't robots, either, but there was so much to learn, it didn't seem that one human skull could hold it all. Down underneath, I think they were afraid my memories of the Virgin of the Rocks—the one in London, I mean, that's the best one—would crowd out my memories of orbital functions. So I made a point of showing off all the astrogational knowledge I had, during rehearsals, and it may have antagonized Baird a little.

Not that we had any fights. We were a tightly woven team when the Benjamin Franklin left the space station and blowtorched for the Moon. It's just—well, maybe we were somewhat more tense than we would have been otherwise.

There were three of us, you remember. Baird was the skipper and pilot, Hernandez the engineer, and I the instrument man, A single person could have handled the ship if nothing went wrong, but three were insurance—any one of us could do any of the other jobs. Also, of course, since this was to be the first actual landing on the Moon, not merely a swing around it, we thought our numbers were peeled down to the bare minimum.

Once in orbit, we hadn't much to do for several days. We floated upward, watching Earth recede and Luna grow against the deepest, blackest, starriest night you have ever imagined. No, you haven't imagined it, either. Pictures don't convey it, the splendor and loneliness.

It was very quiet in the ship. We talked of little things.to keep that silence at arm's length. I remember one conversation pretty well and it touches on the why of all this secrecy.

Earth hung sapphire in the middle of darkness and the stars. Long white auroral streamers shook from the poles like banners. Did you know that, seen from such a distance, our planet has belts? Very much like Jupiter. It's harder than you'd believe to distinguish the continental outlines.

"I think that's Russia coming into view," I said.

Baird glanced at the chronometers and the orbital schedule taped to the wall, and worked his slipstick a minute. "Yeah," he grunted. "Siberia ought to be emerging from the terminator right about now."

"Are they watching us?" murmured Hernandez.

"Sure," I said, "They've got a space station of their own, haven't they, and good telescopes on it?"

"Won't they grin if we barge into a meteor!" said Hernandez.

"If they haven't already arranged an accident," grumbled Baird. "I'm not a damn bit sure they're behind us in astronautics."

"They wouldn't be sorry to see us come to grief," I said, "but I doubt if they'd actually sabotage us. Not a trip like this, with everybody watching."

"It might start the war?" said Baird. "Not a chance. Nobody's going to wipe out a nation—knowing his own will be clobbered, too—for three spacemen and a ten-million-dollar hunk of ship."

"Sure," I replied, "but one thing can lead to another. A diplomatic note can be the first link in a chain ending at war. With the antipodal hydrogen missile available to both sides, you get an interesting state of affairs. The primary aim of national policy has become the preservation of the status quo, but at the same time the tension created makes that status quo exceedingly unstable.

"Do you think our own government would- be sending us to the Moon if there were any military benefit to be gained? Hell, no! The first thing which looks as though it will tip the balance in favor of one side will make the other side go to war, and that means the probable end of civilization. We gain points—prestige—by the first Lunar landing, but not a nickel more. Even as it is, you'll note the Moon is going to be international territory directly under the U.N. That is, nobody dares claim it, because there just might be something of real strategic value there."

"How long can such a balance exist?" wondered Hernandez.

"Till some accident—say, a hothead getting into power in Russia, or anywhere else, for that matter—touches off the attack and the retaliation," I said. "Or there's the faint hope that we'll come up with a gadget absolutely revolutionary—oh, a force screen able to shield a continent—before they have any inkling of it. Then we'll present the world with a fait accompli and the Cold War will be over."

"Unless the Russians get that- screen first," said Hernandez. "Then it'll be over, too, but the bad guys will have won the bloodless victory."

"Shut up," snapped Baird. "You both talk too much."

It had been the wrong thing for me to say, I knew, out there in the great quiet night. We shouldn't have carried our little hates and fears and greeds beyond the sky and out into space.

Or perhaps the fact that we can be burdened with them and still reach the Moon shows that Man is bigger than he knows. I couldn't say.

The waiting wore us down, that and the free-fall. It's easy enough to get used to zero gravity while you're awake, but your instincts aren't so docile. We'd go to sleep and have nightmares. Toward the end of the trip, it happened less often, so I suppose you can get completely adjusted in time.

But we felt no dramatic sense of pioneering when we came down. We were very tired and very tense. It was merely a hard breakneck job.

Our landing site hadn't been chosen exactly, since a small orbital error could make a big difference as far as the Lunar surface was concerned. We could only be sure that it would be near the north pole and not on one of the maria, which look invitingly smooth but are probably treacherous. In point of fact, as you remember, we landed at the foot of the Lunar Alps, not far from the crater Plato. It was rugged country, but our gear had been designed for such a place.

And when the thunder of blasts had faded and our deafened ears tolled slowly toward quiet, we sat. We sat for minutes without a word being spoken. My clothes were plastered to me with sweat

"Well," said Baird at length. "Well, here we are."

He unstrapped himself and reached for the mike and called the station. Hernandez and I crowded the periscopes to see what lay outside.

It was eerie. I've been in deserts on Earth, but they don't blaze so bright, they aren't so absolutely dead, and the rocks aren't so huge and razor-cornered. The southern horizon was near; I thought I could see the surface curve away and tumble off into a foam of stars.

Presently we drew lots. Hernandez got the small one and stayed inside, while I had the privilege of first setting foot on the Moon. Baird and I donned our spacesuits and dumped out through the airlock. Even on Luna, those suits weighed plenty.

We stood in the shadow of the ship, squinting through glare filters. It wasn't a totally black, knife-edged shadow— there was reflection from the ground and the hills—but it was deeper and sharper than any you'll see on Earth. Behind us, the mountains rose high and cruelly shaped. Ahead of us, the land sloped rough, cracked, ocherous toward the rim of Plato, where it shouldered above that toppling horizon. The light was too brilliant for me to see many stars.

You may recall we landed near sunset and figured to leave shortly after dawn, two weeks later. At night on the Moon, the temperature reaches 250 below zero, but the days are hot enough to fry you. And it's easier—takes less mass—to heat the ship .from the pile than to install a refrigerating unit.

"Well," said Baird, "go ahead."

"Go ahead and what ?" I asked.

"Make the speech. You're the first man on the Moon."

"Oh, but you're the captain," I said. "Wouldn't dream of —no, no, Boss. I insist."

You probably read that speech in the papers. It was supposed to have been extemporaneous, but it was written by the wife of somebody way upstairs who believed her daim to be a poet. A verbal emetic, wasn't it? And Baird wanted me to deliver it!

"This is mutiny," he grumbled.

"May I suggest that the captain write in the log that the speech was delivered ?" I said.

"Judas priest!" he snarled. But he did that, later. You understand you're hearing this under the Top Secret label, don't you?

Baird remained in a foul temper. "Get some rock samples," he ordered, setting up the camera. "And on the double! I'm being cooked alive."

I picked loose some of the material, thinking that the traces I left would probably last till the Sun burned out. It seemed an act of desecration, though Lord knew this landscape was ugly enough—

No, I thought, it wasn't. It was only so foreign to us. Do you know, it was several hours before I could really see everything? It took that long for my brain to get used to some of those impressions and start registering them.

Baird was taking pictures. "I wonder if this lighting can be photographed," I remarked. "It isn't like anything that ever shone on Earth." And it wasn't. I can't describe the difference. Think of some of the weird illuminations we get on Earth like that brass-colored light just before a storm, things like that—and multiply the strangeness of them a millionfold.

"Of course it'll photograph," said Baird.

"Oh, yes. In a way," I said. "But to get the feel of it, you'd need such a painter as hasn't lived for centuries. Rembrandt? No, it's too harsh for him, a cold light that's somehow hell-hot, too—"

"Shut up!" The radio voice nearly broke my earphones. "You and your blasted Renaissance!"

After a while, we went inside again. Baird was still mad at me. Unreasonable, but he'd been under a breaking strain, and he still was, and perhaps this wasn't the right place to chat about art.

We fiddled around with our instruments, took what observations were possible, had a meal and a nap. The shadows crept across the land as the Sun rolled downhill. It was a very slow movement. Hernandez examined my rock samples and said that while he wasn't a geologist, this didn't look like anything on Earth. We were told later that it was new to the experts. Same minerals, but crystallized differently under those fantastic conditions.

After our rest, we noticed that the low Sun and the irregular landscape had joined to give us a broad, nearly continuous band of shade dear to Plato Crater. Hernandez suggested we use the chance to explore. It would be after sunset before we could get back, but the ground wouldn't cool off so fast that we couldn't return with the help of our battery packs. In sunless vacuum, you don't lose heat very fast by radiation; it's the Lunar rock, cold to the core, which sucks it out through your boots.

Baird argued, for the record, but he was eager himself. So, in the end, we all set out and to hell with doctrine.

I won't describe that walk in detail. I can't. It wasn't simply the landscape and the lighting. On the Moon, your weight is only one-sixth as much as on Earth, while the inertia remains the same. It feels a bit like walking under water. But you can move fast, once you get the hang of it.

When we came to the ringwall, there were still a couple of hours till sundown, and we climbed it. Tricky work in that undiffused dazzle and those solid-looking shadows, but not very hard. There was an easy slope at the spot we picked and a kind of pass on top, so we didn't have to dimb the full height, which is a little under 4000 feet.

When we reached the summit, we could look down on a lava plain sixty miles across; the farther side was hidden from us. It seemed almost like polished black metal, crossed by the long shadow of the western ringwall. The downward grade was steeper, its base lost in darkness, but it could also be negotiated.

My helmet, sticking into the direct sunlight, was a Dutch oven; my feet, in the shade, were frozen dods. But I forgot all that when I saw the mist below me.

Have you heard of it? Astronomers have noticed it for a long time, what seemed to be douds or—something—in some of the craters. Plato is one. I'd been hoping we'd solve the mystery this trip. And there, curling in ragged streamers a quarter mile below me, was the fog!

It boiled out of the murk, glowed like gold for a moment as it hit the light, and then it was gone, evaporated, but more came rolling up every minute. Not a big patch, this one couldn't have been seen from Earth, but—

I started down the wall. "Hey!" cried Baird. "Get back here!"

"Just a look," I pleaded.

"And you break your leg and have to be carried home, with the night coming on? No!"

"I can't break anything in this suit," I told him. True enough. Space armor is solid metal on the outside—even those trick expanding joints are metal—and the plastic helmet is equally strong. I suppose a man could fall hard enough to kill himself on the Moon, if he really tried, but it would take some doing.

"Come back or I'll have you court-martialed," said Baird between his teeth.

"Show a heart, Skipper," begged Hernandez.

Eventually he talked Baird around. It was only me the captain was irritated with. We roped ourselves together and made a cautious descent.

The mist was coming out of a fissure about halfway down the wall. Where the shadows fell, our lights showed it collecting in hoarfrost on the rocks, then boiling gently away again. After dark, it would settle as ice till dawn. What was it? Water. There's a water table of some kind, I guess, and—I don't know. It suggests there may be indigenous life on the Moon, some low form of plant life maybe, but we didn't find any while we were there. What we found was—

A broad ledge lay just beneath the fissure. We scrambled to it and stood looking up.

Now you'll have to visualize the layout. We were on this ledge, several yards across, with the ringwall jutting sheer above and a cliff falling below into blackness. Far away, I could see the steely glimmer of the crater floor. The ground was all covered with the fine meteoric dust of millions of years; I saw my footprints sharp and dear and knew they might last forever, or until thermal agitation and new dustfall blurred them.

Ten feet overhead was the fissure, like a petrified mouth, and the mist came out of it and smoked upward. It formed almost a roof, a thin ceiling between us and the sky. And the Sim was behind the upper wall, invisible to us. The peaks reflected some of its beams down through the fog.

So we stood there in a cold, faintly golden-white radiance, a fog-glow—God! There's never been such light on Earth! It seemed to pervade everything, drenching us, cold and white, like silence made luminous. It was the light of Nirvana.

And I had seen it once before.

I couldn't remember where. I stood there in that totally alien dream-light, with the mist swirling and breaking overhead, with the stillness of eternity humming in my earphones and my soul, and I forgot everything except the chill, calm, incredible loveliness of it—

But I had seen it somewhere, sometime, and I couldn't remember—

Hernandez yelled.

Baird and I jerked from our thoughts and lumbered to him. He stood crouched a few feet away, staring and staring.

I looked at the ground and something went hollow in me. There were footprints.

We didn't even ask if one of us had made them. Those weren't American' spaceboots. And they had come from below. They had climbed the wall and stood here for a while, scuffed and paced around, and presently we located the trail going back down.

The silence felt like a fiddle string ready to snap.

Baird raised his head at last and gazed before him. The light made his face a thing of unhuman beauty, and somewhere I had seen a face lit that way. I had looked at it, losing myself, for half an hour or more, but when, in what forgotten dream?

"Who?" whispered Baird.

"There's only one country that could send a spaceship to the Moon secretly," said Hernandez in a dead voice.

"British," I croaked. "French—"

"We'd know about it, if they had."

"Russians. Are they still here?" I looked down into the night welling up in Plato.

"No telling," said Baird. "Those tracks could be five hours or five million years old."

They were the prints of hobnailed boots. They weren't excessively large, but judging from the length of the stride, even here on the Moon, they had belonged to a tall man.

"Why haven't they told the world?" asked Hernandez wildly. "They could brag it up so—"

"Why do you think?" rasped Baird.

I looked south. Earth was in half phase, low above the horizon, remote and infinitely fair. I thought America was facing us, but couldn't be sure.

There was only one reason to keep this trip a secret. They had found- something which would upset the "military balance, doubtless in their favor. At this moment, there on Earth, the Kremlin was readying the enslavement of all the human race.

"But how could they have done it secretly?" I protested.

"Maybe they took off in a black ship when our space station was on the other side of the planet. Shut up!" Baird stood without moving.

The Sun went lower, that eldritch light died away, and the blue radiance of Earth took its place. Our faces grew corpse-colored behind the helmets.

"Come on," said Baird. He whirled around. "Let's get back to the ship. They have to know about this in Washington."

"If the Russians know we know, it may start the war," I said.

"I've got a code."

"Are you sure it can't be broken? That it hasn't already been?"

"You trouble-making whelp!" he shouted in a fury. "Be quiet, I tell you!"

"We'd better have a closer look," said Hernandez gently. "Follow those prints and see."

"We didn't bring any weapons," said Baird. "I'd be surprised if the Russians were as careless."

I won't detail the arguments. It was finally settled that I would look further while Baird and Hernandez returned. I had about an hour to follow that trail, then must hurry home if I didn't want to freeze solid.

I looked back once and saw a space-armored shape black across the stars. There were more stars every minute as the sunlight faded and my pupils expanded. Then the shadows walled me in.

It was a rough climb, but a quick one. The stone here was dark and brittle; I could track the stranger by the lighter spots where he'd flaked off chips as he scrambled. I wondered why those spots should be lighter when there was no oxygen around, but decided a photochemical effect was involved.

It was hard to see my way in the shade. The flashbeam was only a puddle of undiffused light before me. But soon I came out in the Earth-glow, and when my eyes had adjusted, it was easy enough. In half an hour, I was on the crater floor. The Sun was behind the ringwalL Black night lay over me.

Not much time to spare. I stood on dark, slick lava and wondered whether to follow those dim footprints in the dust. It might be a long way. Then I shrugged and went bounding off, faster than the other man had gone.

My heart thudded, the suit filled with stale air, it was hard to see the trail by Earthlight. I was more aware of those discomforts than of any danger to my life.

I was a little past the limit of safety when I found the ramp

There wasn't much to see. A long track of plowed dust and chipped stone, where something with runners had landed and taken off again . . . but no sign of a rocket blast! A few scars where a pick had removed samples. Footprints. That was all.

I stood there with the crater wall a loom of night behind me and the mist rising thicker, blue-tinged now. I stood thinking about somebody who landed without needing rockets and never told anyone. I looked around the sky and saw the ruddy speck of Mars and felt cold. Had the Martians beaten us to our own Moon ?

But I had to get back. Every minute I lingered whittled down the chance of my returning at all.

One more look—

There was a little outcrop of granite not far away. I thought it might be a cairn, but when I got there, I saw it was natural. I shrugged and turned to go.

Something caught my eye. I looked closer.

The rock was sleet-colored in the Earthlight. It had one flat surface, facing my planet. And there was a cross hacked into the stone.

I forgot time and the gathering cold. I stood there, thinking, wondering if the cross was merely a coincidental symbol or if there had also, on Mars or on some planet of another star, been One who—

The million suns wheeled and glittered above me.

Then I knew. I remembered where I had seen that light .which lay on the wall at sundown, and I knew the truth.

I turned and started running.

I almost didn't make it. My batteries gave out five miles from the ship. I reported over the radio and continued moving to keep warm, but my feet quickly froze, I stumbled, and each minute the cold deepened.

Baird met me halfway, ripped off my pack and connected another unit.

"You moron!" he snapped. "You blind, bloody, pudding-brained idiot! I'm going to have you up before a court-martial if—"

"Even if I tell you who that was in Plato?" I asked. "Huh?"

We were in the ship and my toes thawing before he got me to explain. It took a lot of talking, but when he grasped the idea—

Of course, Intelligence has been working overtime ever since we came home and told them. They've established now that there was no Russian expedition. But Baird and Hernandez and I have known it ever since our first night on the Moon.

And that, Professor, is the reason you've been drafted. We're going overseas together, officially as tourists. You'll search the archives and I'll tell you if you've found anything useful. I doubt very much if you will. That secret was well kept, like the secret of the submarine, which he also thought should not be given to a warring world. But if somewhere, somehow, we find only a scribbled note, a hint, I'll be satisfied.

It couldn't have been done by rockets, you see. Even if the physics had been known, which it wasn't, the chemistry and metallurgy weren't there. But something else was stumbled on. Antigravity? Perhaps. Whatever it may be, if we can find it, the Cold War will be won ... by free men.

Whether or not we dig up any notes, our research men are busy. Just knowing that such a gadget is possible is a tremendous boost, so you can understand why this must be kept secret.

You don't get it? Professor, I am shocked and grieved. And you a historian! A cultured man!

All right, then. We'll go via London and you'll stop at the National Gallery and sit down in front of a painting called The Virgin of the Rocks. And you will see a light, cold and pale and utterly gentle, a light which never shone on Earth, playing over the Mother and Child. And the artist was Leonardo da Vinci.